<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Statics Must Die! - Writings by Corstijan Kortsmit</title>
    <link>https://staticsmustdie.net/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Statics Must Die! - Writings by Corstijan Kortsmit</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Corstijan Kortsmit 2021</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 16:38:04 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://staticsmustdie.net/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Getting brave with Dapr</title>
      <link>https://staticsmustdie.net/post/brave-dapr/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 16:38:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://staticsmustdie.net/post/brave-dapr/</guid>
      <description>A standardized library available to help developers in things like look-ups, persistence, security or messaging, has been a goal for platform creators since before even J2EE was first released. Today, we look at the latest incarnation of this goal. It&amp;rsquo;s called DAPR, and it&amp;rsquo;s made by Microsoft. Let&amp;rsquo;s go!
Oh no, he didn&amp;rsquo;t Did he compare the latest hippest, fanciest, shiny technology to hit the market with the old-aged brontosaurus that is Java Enterprise?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crossing Styx - My journey into the (under)world of .NET - Part III</title>
      <link>https://staticsmustdie.net/post/2017-03-04-dotnetcore-adventures-iii/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://staticsmustdie.net/post/2017-03-04-dotnetcore-adventures-iii/</guid>
      <description>In the third part of the series, our adventure is slowly but surely heading to its climax. All &amp;lsquo;characters&amp;rsquo; have been introduced. There&amp;rsquo;s DotNet Core, the new, misunderstood (or at least by me?) kid with a bunch of talent. Docker, the awesome supporting character that actually deserves his own movie. Surely there&amp;rsquo;ll be a spin-off! There&amp;rsquo;s the antagonist, Jenkins, who might end up working along with our main character more then either had hoped for.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crossing Styx - My journey into the (under)world of .NET - Part II</title>
      <link>https://staticsmustdie.net/post/2017-02-05-dotnetcore-adventures-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://staticsmustdie.net/post/2017-02-05-dotnetcore-adventures-ii/</guid>
      <description>In my previous post on this topic, I somehow got the jitters to get started with .NET. Or more specifically, .NET core. Being stubborn as I am, I have created a simple delivery pipeline in Jenkins, for building and deploying a .NET core docker container.
Now, this might sound like hell freezing over. Me, programming .NET? Blasphemy! Except one little thing. For my previous post, I didn&amp;rsquo;t actually write one line of C# code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crossing Styx - My journey into the (under)world of .NET - Part I</title>
      <link>https://staticsmustdie.net/post/2017-01-16-dotnetcore-adventures-i/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://staticsmustdie.net/post/2017-01-16-dotnetcore-adventures-i/</guid>
      <description>At the closing of last year, I presented an in-house talk, comparing Continuous Delivery solutions for both Java and .NET. Of course, this was not a simple side-by-side comparison; a microsoft oriented colleague and myself created a small challenge for ourselves. My colleague was going to build Java software in Team Foundation Server. And me? I was stuck creating a delivery pipeline for Microsoft .NET in Jenkins.
Now, I had been thinking about looking into .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>System.out.println(&#34;Hello World&#34;)</title>
      <link>https://staticsmustdie.net/post/2016-12-27-hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://staticsmustdie.net/post/2016-12-27-hello-world/</guid>
      <description>Greetings, dear reader, and welcome to my little corner of the web. It&amp;rsquo;s nearing the end of 2016, and I have decided I want to start my resolution of finally putting up some blogs before 2017 enters with a bang.
Or, at the very least, have a welcoming blog post up and running. Minimal Viable Product and all. So, with that ,I bid you welcome to Statics Must Die, the ramblings of me, Corstijan Kortsmit.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
